Guide to the Morgan-Parry family papers 1990.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
Morgan-Parry family papers
1861-1909
Brooklyn Historical Society
Morgan, Henry C.
Morgan-Parry family
1990.006
0.8 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and one half manuscript box.
The Morgan-Parry family papers include the official and personal papers of Henry C. Morgan and Augusta Parry Morgan. Materials of an official nature include documents and correspondence of Henry C. Morgan relating to his work as a 1st Lieutenant in the 12th infantry of the U.S. Army, and later as Captain in the 30th Regiment of the Infantry. Personal materials include correspondence and letters relating to Henry and Augusta, as well as their daughter Mary and Augusta's father, Edward O. Parry. The collection contains a contract for Henry and Augusta's residence on Clinton Street dating from December 1870. The collection contains five portraits, which include the following people: A.V. Lt. E. Cooker (?), Lt. Col. Henry C. Morgan, Mary Churchill Morgan, William A. Stedman, Jr., and Mr. and Mrs. William Witman. It also contains two cards containing images and plans of the Royal Mail Steam Ship Scotia.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth Stookey, 1990.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by type.
Biographical note
Henry C. Morgan was born in Brooklyn on December 30, 1842. His father was N.D. Morgan, President of the North America Life Insurance Company in New York, and his uncle was Edwin Denison Morgan, who served as Governor of New York and later was a United States Senator. During the Civil War, Edwin D. Morgan served as major general of Volunteers in the Union Army (1861-1863). Henry worked as clerk for the Manhattan Life Insurance Company before being enlisted to serve in the Civil War as a Recruiting Officer in October of 1861.
While recruiting service in Pottsville, Pennsylvania, Henry met his future wife, Augusta "Gussie" Parry. After being wounded in Virginia in 1864, requiring amputation of his left leg above the knee, Henry left service, and he and Augusta were married in April of 1865. The couple had three daughters, Mary, Ruth, and Kate, and settled in Brooklyn at 446 Clinton Street. Henry's brother, William G. Morgan and his wife Elizabeth C. Morgan resided next door at 448 Clinton Street. Later, the family moved to Colchester, Connecticut.
In 1875, Henry C. Morgan made several inquiries into the manufacturing of, and then secured a patent for, a toy pistol called the "Centennial Toy Pistol."
Henry C. Morgan died on February 5, 1906. Augusta followed on September 28, 1910. They are buried beside each other in Linwood Cemetery, Colchester, Connecticut.
Related Materials
Civil War collection (1977.200)
Frank J. Bramhall Civil War collection (1977.006)
Scope and Contents
The Morgan-Parry family papers include the official and personal papers of Henry C. Morgan and Augusta Parry Morgan. Materials of an official nature include documents and correspondence of Henry C. Morgan relating to his work as a 1st Lieutenant in the 12th infantry of the U.S. Army, and later as Captain in the 30th Regiment of the Infantry. Personal materials include correspondence and letters relating to Henry and Augusta, as well as their daughter Mary and Augusta's father, Edward O. Parry. The collection contains two contracts for Henry and Augusta's residence on Clinton Street dating from December 1870. The collection also contains five portraits, which include the following people: A.V. Lt. E. Cooker, Lt. Col. Henry C. Morgan, Mary Churchill Morgan, William A. Stedman, Jr., and Mr. and Mrs. William Witman. It also contains two cards containing images and plans of the Royal Mail Steam Ship Scotia.
Separated Materials
Henry C. Morgan's wallet is stored with the Art and Artifact collections under the object ID M1990.34.1.
Photographs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Correspondence; Portraits; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Equipment and supplies; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- History, Military; Military ceremonies, honors, and salutes -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Military commissions; Military life; Military records; Orders (military records); Financial records; Receipts (financial records); Hair (material); Dried flowers; Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.); Fort Hamilton (New York, N.Y.); Morgan, Henry C.; Morgan-Parry family
- Series 1: Henry C. Morgan official documents
  - Invoices, 1861-1866 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rejections, 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipts, 1861-1868 (Box 1, Folder 3, Folder Flat File)
  - Special orders and circulars, 1861-1868 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial monthly statements, 1862-1864 (Folder Flat File)
  - Vouchers, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Returns of ordnance, 1863-1867 (Box 1, Folder 6, Folder Flat File)
  - Transfers of ordnance stores, 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificates of losses, 1864-1868 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Commissions, 1865-1867 (Box 1, Folder 9, Folder Flat File)
  - Certificate of membership of the Loyal Legion, 1868 (Folder Flat File)
  - Inventories, 1861-1863 (Box 1, Folder 10, Folder Flat File)
  - Financial documents, 1862, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 11, Folder Flat File)
  - Personnel records, 1862-1866 (Box 1, Folder 12, Folder Flat File)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes documents regarding rations, muster rolls, and payroll.
  - Correspondence, 1861-1868 (Box 1, Folder 13-15, Folder Flat File)
  - Correspondence: Letterbooks, 1862-1867 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
- Series 2: Morgan-Parry family
  - Henry C. Morgan private correspondence, 1860-1902 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Henry C. Morgan correspondence: manufacturing of toy pistols, 1874-1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Henry C. Morgan correspondence: purchase of horse, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Augusta P. Morgan correspondence and marriage certificate, 1862-1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Also includes a small clipping announcing the Morgans' marriage.
  - Edward O. Parry correspondence, 1863-1878 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with other family members, 1846-1907 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Construction contracts, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    For two properties on Clinton Street between Carroll Street and First Place in Carroll Gardens.
  - Mary C. Morgan materials, 1880-1906 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes pressed flowers.
  - Wills of Henry C. and Augusta P. Morgan, 1873, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Henry C. Morgan notebook, circa 1873 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes pressed leaves between some pages.
  - Legal documents: Edwin D. Morgan estate, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Calling cards, clippings and ephemera, circa 1860s-1890 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Includes pressed leaves, a photograph mounted on card and a lock of Augusta P. Morgan's hair.
  - Photographs, circa 1860 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes two images of Royal Mail steam ship Scotia, E. Cooker, Henry C. Morgan, William A. Stedman, Jr. and wife Mary Churchill Morgan, Mrs. William Witman, and William Witman.